<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../../module.rnc" schematypens="https://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<module id="top">
  <h lang="en">mar</h>
  <h lang="gd">mar</h>
  <p lang="en">Examples – <xl id="exs">
      <li>
        <gd>[...] A nis, tha an Taghadh Nàiseanta seachad, agus tha Riaghaltas ùr againn. Tha sinn
          an dòchas gun téid gu math dhaibh, agus gun cuir iad spionnadh ás ùr anns an dùthaich air
          fad. Agus gu seachd àraidh anns a’ Ghaidhealtachd: gun tòisich obair an dealain a rithist,
          gun cuirear tuilleadh bhàtaichean-iasgaich an sàs, gum faigh na Gaidheil cothrom air
          fearann na Gaidhealtachd obrachadh dhaibh fhéin, ás bith an ann <m>mar chroitean no mar
            innis no mar choille</m>, gun bhacadh o bhàllidh no o thighearna.</gd>
        <tr>[...] Now, the General Election is behind us, and we have a new Government. We hope that
          they will do well, and that they will re-energise the whole country. And most especially
          in the Highlands: that electricity work will restart, that more fishing boats will be put
          into service [?], that the Gaels will get the opportunity to work the land of the
          Highlands for themselves, whether <u>as crofts or as grazing or as forest</u>, without
          hindrance from a bailiff or from a laird.</tr>
        <ref text="400-49">td. 9, ‘Air an Spiris’</ref>
      </li>
    </xl>
  </p>
  <p lang="gd">...</p>

  <module id="mar_sin_air_adhart">
    <h lang="en">agus mar sin air adhart</h>
    <h lang="gd">agus mar sin air adhart</h>
    <p lang="en">Examples – <xl id="msaa-exs">
        <li>
          <gd>[...] ’Se glé bheag de chobhair a thug a’ Phàrlamaid a riamh do ’n Ghàidhlig no do
            fhoghlum agus do litreachas na Gàidhlig. [...] Dé na rudan a dh’ fhaodadh sinn iarraidh?
            Tuilleadh de luchd-teagaisg ’s de luchd-ceasnachaidh Gàidhlig. Airgead gu leabhraichean
            uallachadh is a chlo-bhualadh. Barrachd tìde air an réidio agus air telebhisean. Dithis
            dhaoine a chur an sàs anns na làmh-sgrìobhainnean Gàidhlig san Leabharlann Nàiseanta,
            agus dithis eile san Ordnance Survey. Barrachd rannsachaidh air caitheamh-beatha nan
            Gaidheal, an cànan, an eachdraidh, an ceòl, <m>is mar sin air adhart</m>.[...]</gd>
          <tr>[...] The Parliament has given very little assistance ever to the Gaelic language or
            to Gaelic education and literature. [...] What are the things that we could demand? More
            Gaelic teachers and inspectors. Money to prepare and print books. More time on the radio
            and on television. Involving two people in the Gaelic manuscripts in the National
            Library, and two others in the Ordnance Survey. More research on the lifestyle of the
            Gaels, their language, their history, their music, <u>and so on</u>. [...]</tr>
          <ref text="400-49">td. 9, ‘Air an Spiris’</ref>
        </li>
      </xl>
    </p>
    <p lang="gd">...</p>
  </module>

  <module id="mar_a">
    <h lang="en">mar a</h>
    <h lang="gd">mar a</h>
    <p lang="en">cf. relative particle <a href="?gd=a^relative">a</a>.</p>
    <p lang="gd">...</p>
    <p lang="en">Examples from Gairm – <xl id="mar_a-gairm">
        <li>
          <gd>Anns na ràithean ’s na bliadhnachan a tha air thoiseach oirnn, tha fhios gun dig
            iomadh atharrachadh air Roinn na Gàidhlig sa’ Bh.B.C. [...] <m>Mar a bhios</m> obair a’
            Bh.B.C. a’ leudachadh anns a’ Ghaidhealtachd—agus tha fhios gun tachair so leis na
            stéiseanan ùra a thathas a’ togail—bithidh sùil againn ri daoine ùra ’s ri dòighean ùra.
            [...]</gd>
          <tr>During the seasons and the years that are ahead of us, it is known that many changes
            will come to the Gaelic Department of the BBC. [...] As the work of the BBC will be
            expanding in the Highlands – and it is known that this will happen with the new stations
            that are being established – we will be expecting new people and new methods. [...]</tr>
          <ref text="400-48">td. 297, ‘Air An Spiris’</ref>
          <note>abstract, passive object extraction</note>
        </li>
        <li>
          <gd>[...] Choisich e mach ás a’ bhàta a-measg nam faoileagan, ga[n] sguabadh air falbh le
            a làmhan, agus lean e air suas an aon rathad a bh’ ann gus an ruigeadh e an tigh. Cha
            robh e duilich tigh Maireid a lorg. “’S iongantach <m>mar a bhios iad a’
              smaoineachadh</m> gur ann a reic rudeigin a thainig mi,” thubhairt e ris fhéin le
            seòrsa de ghàire, ’s e a’ sealltainn ris an inneal a bha e slaodadh. Bha Mairead ’na
            suidhe ann an cathair ris an teine is plaide timcheall air a glùinean. [...]</gd>
          <tr>[...] He walked out of the boat among the gulls, brushing them away with his hands,
            and he continued up the only road that there was until he reached the house. It was not
            difficult to find Margaret’s house. Margaret was sat in a chair by the fire with a
            blanket around her knees. [...]</tr>
          <ref text="400-46">td. 169, le Iain Mac a’ Ghobhainn</ref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <gd>[...] “Rinn e òran dhomh. Oran briagha.” Thainig lasadh de bhòidhchead charach ’na
            h-aodann. “Cha robh sinn ach fichead bliadhna a dh’ aois.” Thainig an samhradh a-steach
            air an uinneig mar bhoireannach. “’Se Sasunnach a bh’ ann,” ars ise le prois, ’s thainig
            facail a-mach ás a beul mar mhionnan, “darling,” “come back,” “remember.” Chunnaic e
            Màiri a’ tionndadh a ceann air falbh ’s dh’aithnich e airson a’ chiad uair <m>mar a tha
              an aois beò ann an rìoghachd gun nàire</m>. [...]</gd>
          <tr>[...] “He sang me a song. A beautiful song.” A glimmer of sly beauty came in [over]
            her face. “We were just twenty years of age.” The summer came in through the window like
            a woman. “He was an Englishman,” she said with pride, and words came out from her mouth
            like curses, [...] He saw Mary turning her head away and he realised for the first time
            how old age is alive in a kingdom without shame [??] [...]</tr>
          <ref text="400-46">td. 170, le Iain Mac a’ Ghobhainn</ref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <gd>[...] Dh’fhàs a guth na bu làidir. “Tha aon rud cinnteach, chan fhalbh aon choigreach
            le mo leanabh. Cha teid i gu aon dannsa, tha sin cinnteach. Tha. Tha. Na bi
            smaoineachadh gun teid, a leanaibh. Chan eil fhios agad mu ’n deidhinn, <m>mar a th’
            agamsa</m>.” “Carson nach do bhàsaich thu o chionn leth-cheud bliadhna,” dh’ éigh
            Màiri. Bha i smaoineachadh air na gnothaichean ud fhathast! [...]</gd>
          <tr>[...] Her voice grew louder. “One thing is certain, not one stranger will leave [go
            out?] with my child. She will not go to a single dance, that is certain. It is. It is.
            Do not be thinking that you will, child. You don’t know about them, as I do.” “Why did
            you not die fifty years ago,” shouted Mary. She was still thinking about those matters!
            [...]</tr>
          <ref text="400-46">td. 171, le Iain Mac a’ Ghobhainn</ref>
        </li>
      </xl></p>
    <p lang="gd">...</p>
    <p lang="en">Biblical examples – <xl id="bible">
        <li>
          <gd>[...] Agus labhair righ na h-Eiphit re mnaibh-glùine nan Eabhruidheach [...] Agus
            thubhairt e, ’Nuair a ni sibh gnìomh mnà-glùine do na mnaibh Eabhruidheach, agus a chi
            sibh iad air na stòlaibh; ma’s mac a bhios ann, ’an sin marbhaidh sibh e, ach ma’s
            nighean a bhios ann, bithidh si beo. Ach bha eagal Dé air na mnaibh-glùine, agus cha
            d’rinn iad <m>mar a dh’àithn righ na h-Eiphit dhoibh</m>, ach ghleidh iad a’ chlann mhac
            beo. [...]</gd>
          <tr>[...] And the king of Egypt spake to the Hebrew midwives [...] And he said, When ye do
            the office of a midwife to the Hebrew women, and see them upon the stools; if it be a
            son, then ye shall kill him: but if it be a daughter, then she shall live. But the
            midwives feared God, and did not as the king of Egypt commanded them, but saved the men
            children alive. [...]</tr>
          <ref text="160">Ecsodus I.15–17</ref>
        </li>
      </xl>
    </p>
    <p lang="gd">...</p>
    <module id="mar_as_motha">
      <h lang="en">mar as motha a ...</h>
      <h lang="gd">mar as motha a ...</h>
      <p lang="en">Biblical examples – <xl id="mar_as_motha-bible">
          <li>
            <gd>[...] A nis dh’éirich righ ùr air an Eiphit, do nach b’aithne Ioseph. Agus thubhairt
              e r’a shluagh, Feuch, tha sluagh chloinn Israeil ni’s lìonmhoire agus ni’s
              cumhachdaiche na sinne. Thigibh, buineamaid gu seòlta : an t-eagal gu’m fàs iad
              lìonmhor, agus gu’n tachair e, ’nuair a dh’éireas cogadh, gu’n gabh iadsan mar an
              ceudna le ’r naimhdibh-ne, agus gu’n cog iad ’nar n-aghaidh, agus gu’n d’théid iad a
              mach as an tìr. Uime sin chuir iad maighstirean-oibre orra, chum an sàrachadh le’n
              eallachaibh. [...] Ach <m>mar is mò a shàraich siad iad, ’s ann is mò a rinneadh
                iadsan lìonmhor agus a dh’fhàs iad</m>. Agus bha iad fuidh dhoilgheas air son
              chloinn Israeil. [...]</gd>
            <tr>[...] Now there arose up a new king over Egypt, which knew not Joseph. And he said
              unto his people, Behold, the people of the children of Israel are more and mightier
              than we: Come on, let us deal wisely with them; lest they multiply, and it come to
              pass, that, when there falleth out any war, they join also unto our enemies, and fight
              against us, and so get them up out of the land. Therefore they did set over them
              taskmasters to afflict them with their burdens. [...] But the more they afflicted
              them, the more they multiplied and grew. And they were grieved because of the children
              of Israel. [...]</tr>
            <ref text="160">Ecsodus I.8-12</ref>
          </li>
        </xl>
      </p>
      <p lang="gd">...</p>
    </module>

  </module>


  <!--
  <title lang="en">mar</title>
  <title lang="gd">mar</title>
  <p lang="en"><strong>mar</strong>
    <en>like, as</en> is a preposition.</p>
  <hr/>
  <p lang="en">Examples of usage –</p>
  <ulx id="exs">
    <lix>
      <gd>Bha feallsanach <m>mar</m> Hegel a’ togail riaghailtean móra a dheanadh an saoghal air a thaobh a-muigh fhéin soilleir, ach cha b’ ann <m>mar</m> sin a bha Kierkegaard.</gd>
      <tr>A philosopher <u>like</u> Hegel constructed grand rules which made the external world itself clear but K. was not <u>like</u> that.</tr>
      <ref text="400-41">td. 103</ref>
    </lix>
  </ulx>
  <hr/>
  <h lang="en">mar sin</h>
  <p lang="en">Examples of usage –</p>
  <ulx id="mar_sin">
    <lix>
      <gd>Bha beagan airgid aige ’s <m>mar sin</m> chaith e a bheatha a’ sgrìobhadh, gun feum aige air obair eile a dhèanamh.</gd>
      <tr>He had a little money and <u>therefore</u> he devoted his life to writing, without the need to do other work.</tr>
      <ref text="400-41">td. 103</ref>
    </lix>
  </ulx>

  <p>The Gaelic particle <strong>mar</strong> is used as a kind of preposition or conjunction, and corresponds to various senses of the English particles ‘like’, ‘as’, and ‘how’.</p>
  <p>Internally, <strong>mar</strong> governs one of the following as its complement:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>a (nominative) noun or pronoun, e.g. <mark>mar chù</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘like a dog’</small>, <mark>mar seo</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘like this’</small></li>
    <li>a (positive) relative clause introduced by the particle <strong>a</strong>, e.g. <mark>mar a sheinn Màiri</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘like Mary sang’</small></li>
    <li>a (positive) noun clause introduced by the particle <strong>gun</strong>, e.g. <mark>mar gum biodh iad sgìth</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘as if they were tired’</small></li>
  </ul>
  <p>Externally, <strong>mar</strong> is governed in one the following ways:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>as the complement of the copular verb <strong>bi</strong>, e.g. <mark>Tha Iain mar chù.</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘John is like a dog.’</small>
      <small><a data-toggle="modal" data-target="#predicative-bi" href="#">[more]</a></small>
    </li>
    <li>as a modifier of a (common) noun, e.g. <mark>aodann mar chù</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘a face like a dog’</small>
      <small><a data-toggle="modal" data-target="#adnominal" href="#">[more]</a></small>
    </li>
    <li>as a ‘manner’ modifier of a verb, <ul>
        <li><strong>mar a</strong>, e.g. e.g. <mark>Dh’ith e mar a sheinn Màiri.</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘He ate like Mary sang.’</small>
          <small><a data-toggle="modal" data-target="#manner-relative" href="#">[more]</a></small>
        </li>
        <li><strong>mar gun</strong>, e.g. e.g. <mark>Dh’ith e mar gun robh an t-uisge ann.</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘He ate as if it were raining.’</small>
          <small><a data-toggle="modal" data-target="#manner-noun-clause" href="#">[more]</a></small>
        </li>
        <li>prepositional, e.g. <mark>Dh’ith e mar chù.</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘He ate like a dog.’</small>
          <small><a data-toggle="modal" data-target="#manner-prepositional" href="#">[more]</a></small>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>as a ‘parenthetical’ adjunct to a clause, e.g. <mark>Mar a h-uile cù, is toil leis isbeanan.</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘Like all dogs, he likes sausages.’</small>
      <ul>
        <li><mark>mar sin</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘therefore’</small></li>
        <li><mark>mar as àbhaist</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘as usual’</small></li>
        <li><mark>mar as trice</mark>
          <small class="text-muted">‘usually’</small></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>as the complement of certain verbs, adjectives and nouns, e.g. <mark>Tha e ag obair mar sgrìobhadair.</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘He is working as a writer.’</small></li>
    <li>as the complement of a copular pronoun, e.g. <mark>Sin mar a sheinn Màiri.</mark>
      <small class="text-muted">‘That is how Mary sang.’</small></li>
  </ul>
  <p>Note that <strong>mar</strong> can, in most of its uses, be intensified with the adverb <strong>dìreach</strong>, i.e. <mark>dìreach mar</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘just like’</small>.</p>
  <hr/>

  <div class="modal fade" id="predicative-bi" tabindex="-1" role="dialog">
    <div class="modal-dialog modal-lg" role="document">
      <div class="modal-content">
        <div class="modal-header">
          <h5 class="modal-title" id="exampleModalLabel"><em>mar</em> as the complement of <em>bi</em></h5>
          <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal">
            <span aria-hidden="true">&times;</span>
          </button>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-body">
          <p>When <strong>mar</strong> governs a (nominative) noun or pronoun, it commonly occurs in a context where it is the predicative complement of the copular verb <strong>bi</strong>, and
            corresponds to the English preposition ‘like’, i.e. <strong>bi mar</strong> ‘be like’. This construction asserts that the entity denoted by the subject of <strong>bi</strong> is
              <em>similar</em> in some significant way to the entity denoted by the noun that <strong>mar</strong> governs. For example:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2789"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2825"/>
          </ul>
          <p>These two examples involve similes – the garden is compared to an oasis, and the man to a lump of iron. In the following example, the target of the comparison is a definite noun, the
            legendary Lewis outlaw <em>Mac an t-Srònaich</em>:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2828"/>
          </ul>
          <p>When <strong>mar</strong> occurs in an ungoverned context, the copular verb is usually understood as being implicit:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2833"/>
          </ul>
          <p>When <strong>mar</strong> is governed by <strong>bi</strong>, it is usually itself prepositional, governing a noun or pronoun. However, occasional examples are found where it governs a
            relative clause:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2919"/>
          </ul>
          <p>[Note: this relative clause contains a ‘gap’, i.e. bu chòir dha bhith mar sin]</p>
          <p>cf. <strong>coltach ri</strong></p>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-footer">
          <button type="button" class="btn btn-secondary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="modal fade" id="adnominal" tabindex="-1" role="dialog">
    <div class="modal-dialog modal-lg" role="document">
      <div class="modal-content">
        <div class="modal-header">
          <h5 class="modal-title" id="exampleModalLabel">Adnominal <em>mar</em></h5>
          <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal">
            <span aria-hidden="true">&times;</span>
          </button>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-body">
          <p>Another common use of prepositional <strong>mar</strong> is as an adnominal, directly modifying another noun. Here, it is usually asserted that the entity denoted by the modified noun is
            similar to the entity denoted by the noun that <strong>mar</strong> governs. For example:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2792"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2846"/>
          </ul>
          <p>The following adnominal example is deceptive in that it is asserted that the two nouns denote the <em>same</em> entity, rather than two distinct but similar entities. It may be an example
            of English influence:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2805"/>
          </ul>
          <p>When used adnominally, <strong>mar</strong> is usually used as a preposition, governing a (nominative) noun or pronoun. However, in the following example, it governs a relative clause and
            appears to modify the noun <strong>cuideachadh</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘assistance’</small>:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2923"/>
          </ul>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-footer">
          <button type="button" class="btn btn-secondary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="modal fade" id="manner-relative" tabindex="-1" role="dialog">
    <div class="modal-dialog modal-lg" role="document">
      <div class="modal-content">
        <div class="modal-header">
          <h5 class="modal-title" id="exampleModalLabel"><em>mar</em> as the complement of <em>bi</em></h5>
          <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal">
            <span aria-hidden="true">&times;</span>
          </button>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-body">
          <p>Another common use of <strong>mar</strong> is as a kind of subordinating conjunction expressing a concept similar to a manner adverb, i.e. modifying a verb and describing in more detail
              <em>how</em> the action denoted by that verb was carried out. When used as a conjunction, <strong>mar</strong> itself governs a verb rather than a noun, and asserts that the action
            denoted by the superordinate verb is similar in manner to the action denoted by the subordinate verb.</p>
          <p>In its first manner adverbal use, <strong>mar</strong> governs a (positive) relative clause, introduced by the relative particle <strong>a</strong>. The verb within the relative clause
            denotes an event which is assumed to have actually happened or which is going to actually happen. This usage corresponds to the English conjunction ‘as’. For example:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2779"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2889"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2880"/>
          </ul>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-footer">
          <button type="button" class="btn btn-secondary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="modal fade" id="manner-noun-clause" tabindex="-1" role="dialog">
    <div class="modal-dialog modal-lg" role="document">
      <div class="modal-content">
        <div class="modal-header">
          <h5 class="modal-title" id="exampleModalLabel"><em>mar</em> as the complement of <em>bi</em></h5>
          <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal">
            <span aria-hidden="true">&times;</span>
          </button>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-body">
          <p>In its second manner adverbal use, <strong>mar</strong> governs a (positive) complement clause, introduced by the dependent verb particle <strong>gun</strong>. The subordinate verb is
            usually a conditional form of <strong>bi</strong> (or a past tense form with conditional force). Here the assumption is that the state denoted by the subordinate clause is purely
            hypothetical. For example:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2841"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2840"/>
          </ul>
          <p>Here are two examples involving cleft constructions:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2838"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2839"/>
          </ul>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-footer">
          <button type="button" class="btn btn-secondary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="modal fade" id="manner-prepositional" tabindex="-1" role="dialog">
    <div class="modal-dialog modal-lg" role="document">
      <div class="modal-content">
        <div class="modal-header">
          <h5 class="modal-title" id="exampleModalLabel"><em>mar</em> as the complement of <em>bi</em></h5>
          <button type="button" class="close" data-dismiss="modal">
            <span aria-hidden="true">&times;</span>
          </button>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-body">
          <p>Prepositional <strong>mar</strong> can also be used to introduce a hypothetical manner adverb, for example:</p>
          <ul>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2794"/>
            <li class="ex" data-slip="2790"/>
          </ul>
          <p>The manner phrases in these examples can be paraphrased as ‘as if he were a lawyer’ and ‘as if we were a squad of soldiers’.</p>
        </div>
        <div class="modal-footer">
          <button type="button" class="btn btn-secondary" data-dismiss="modal">Close</button>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>


  <h3>3. Other adverbal uses of <em>mar</em></h3>
  <p><mark>mar sin</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘therefore’</small>, <mark>mar as àbhaist</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘as usual’</small>, <mark>mar as trice</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘usually’</small>, <mark>mar a thuirt i</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘as she said’</small>, etc. <small><a data-toggle="collapse" href="#other-adverbal">more/less</a></small></p>
  <div class="collapse" id="other-adverbal">
    <p>Both as a preposition and a conjunction, <strong>mar</strong> is used in a range of other, more idiomatic adverbal expressions.</p>
    <h5>
      <em>mar sin</em>
    </h5>
    <p>‘so’, ‘therefore’, ‘for that reason’</p>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2768"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2771"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2774"/>
    </ul>
    <h5>mar as àbhaist</h5>
    <p>‘as usual’</p>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2907"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2910"/>
    </ul>
    <p>cf. <strong>àbhaist</strong></p>
    <h5>mar as trice</h5>
    <p>‘usually’</p>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2884"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2914"/>
    </ul>
    <p>cf. <strong>tric</strong></p>
    <h5>mar a thuirt i</h5>
    <p>‘as she said’</p>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2895"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2905"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2897"/>
    </ul>
    <p>Note that future and conditional forms of the irregular verb <strong>abair</strong> are usually avoided in many modern dialects, in favour of either forms of the regular verb
        <strong>can</strong> or progressive constructions with the verbal noun <strong>ràdh</strong>.</p>
    <h5>Others</h5>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2780"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2781"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2917"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2888"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2921"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2924"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2926"/>
    </ul>
    <p>Prepositional:</p>
    <ul>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2783"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2791"/>
      <li class="ex" data-slip="2807"/>
    </ul>
  </div>

  <h3>4. Complement uses of <em>mar</em></h3>
  <h5>(a) Employment ‘as’</h5>
  <p><mark>Tha mo bhean ag obair mar thidsear.</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘My wife works as a teacher.’</small>
    <small><a data-toggle="collapse" href="#complement-employment">more/less</a></small></p>
  <div class="collapse" id="complement-employment">
    <p>Prepositional <strong>mar</strong> can also be used to introduce the complement of a verb, noun or adjective. Many of these cases involve the semantic domain of ‘employment’:</p>
    <table class="table">
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>ag obair mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘working as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2837"/>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2801"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>suidhich mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘appoint as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2835"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>dreuchd mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘a job/career as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2803"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>dèan beòshlaint mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘make a living as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2782"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </div>
  <h5>(b) Evaluation/perception/reputation ‘as’</h5>
  <p><mark>Tha Raonaid a’ meas a’ Phrìomh Mhinisteir mar dearg-amadan.</mark>
    <small class="text-muted">‘Rachel regards the Prime Minister as a complete fool.’</small>
    <small><a data-toggle="collapse" href="#complement-evaluation">more/less</a></small></p>
  <div class="collapse" id="complement-evaluation">
    <p>Other examples involve ‘evaluation’, ‘perception’ and ‘reputation’ words:</p>
    <table class="table">
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>meas mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘regard something as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2830"/>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2784"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>coimhead air ... mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘see something as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2831"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>smaoinich air ... mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘think of something as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2834"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>ainmeil / iomraiteach mar</strong>
            <small class="text-muted">‘well-known as’</small></td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2802"/>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2809"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </div>
  <h5>(c) Others</h5>
  <p><mark/>
    <small class="text-muted">‘.’</small>
    <small><a data-toggle="collapse" href="#complement-other">more/less</a></small></p>
  <div class="collapse" id="complement-other">
    <table class="table">
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>air a sgeadachadh mar</strong> ‘dressed as’</td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2804"/>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2810"/>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2824"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>sgrìobh mar</strong> ‘write as’</td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2832"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><strong>tachartasan mar</strong> ‘one’s exploits as’</td>
          <td>
            <ul>
              <li class="ex" data-slip="2826"/>
            </ul>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </div>


  <h3>5. Embedded questions / free relatives</h3>
  <p>Free relatives (as dialectal alternative to <strong>na</strong>):</p>
  <ul>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2844"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
  </ul>
  <p>Embedded questions (as dialectal alternative to <strong>ciamar a</strong>):</p>
  <ul>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2886"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2883"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2800"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2778"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2912"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2929"/>
  </ul>
  <p>Unclear:</p>
  <ul>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2882"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2911"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2913"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2847"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip="2885"/>
    <li class="ex" data-slip=""/>
  </ul>
  -->
</module>
