<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../module.rnc" schematypens="https://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<module>
  <title>deannan</title>
  <p><strong>deannan</strong>
    <en>small amount, little, few</en> is a masculine <a href="?xx=nouns/generic_quantity_nouns">generic quantity noun</a>, a diminutive of the feminine noun <strong>deann</strong>
    <en>particle</en>. Dictionaries list the genitive singular form <strong>deannain</strong> and the plural <strong>deannanan</strong>, though it is not clear the extent to which these are used.</p>
  <hr/>
  <p>In terms of the stuff being quantified, <strong>deannan</strong> generally works like other generic quantity nouns –</p>
  <ul>
    <li>When the stuff being quantified is new information, it is usually expressed as a noun modifier/specifier of <strong>deannan</strong>, either the genitive singular of a mass noun or the
      genitive plural of a count noun eg. <ul>
        <li>Dh’òl Raonaid <m>deannan <u>fìona</u></m>. <en>Rachel drank a little wine.</en></li>
        <li>Tha <m>deannan <u>chon</u></m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has a few dogs.</en></li>
      </ul>
      <ulx id="deannan_specifier">
        <li>
          <gd>Nis bha na làithean a’ dol seachad agus na seachduinnean cuideachd, ’s cha robh Alasdair a’ brath creic fhaotainn do’n Dolaidh Anna. 
            Ràinig deannan choigrich ’ga coimhead, ceart gu leòr,
            ach cha robh ann ach aon duine a bha cho fad air ais ’s gun robh an coltas air gum faodadh cumadh glan agus peanta dheàrrsach a mhealladh.</gd>
          <tr>Now the days were going by and the weeks as well, and Alexander was not [managing to?] find a buyer for Dollyanna [a boat]. 
              A few strangers came to see her, true enough, but there was only one man who was so [old-fashioned?] that he looked as 
              though a [clean shape]? and bright paint might deceive him.</tr>
          <ref text="44">td. 29</ref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <gd>Bha sinn glé thric ag iasgach. B’e sin an t-iasgach – iasgach phartan, gun slat, gun dubhan ach pìos sreinge agus sgonn mhath biadhaidh air a ceann: 
            earrann mhath de rionnach saillte a fhuaireadh a thoirt gu falchaidh as a’ bharailte a bha san taigh bheag aig ceann an taighe. 
            Nuair a gheibhte deannan phartan, dh’fhalbhamaid an sin a dhèanamh fang, a’ toirt a chreidsinn
            oirnn fhìn gur ann a bh’againn caoraich.</gd>
          <tr>We went fishing a lot. That was the fishing – fishing for crabs, without a rod, without a hook, 
            only a piece of string and a good lump of bait at the end: a good piece of salted mackerel that was [snuck?] 
            from the barrel that was in the little shed at the end of the house. When a few crabs were found, we left [there] to make a pen,
            pretending to ourselves that we had sheep.</tr>
          <ref text="28">td. 7</ref></li>
        <li>
          <gd>Bhiodh sgur ga chur air iasgach an sgadain sa’ Mhaoil airson deannan sheachdainean o mheadhoin na Giblein 
            gu cothrom a thoirt dhan iasg tighinn gu abaichead.</gd>
          <tr>The herring fishing was stopped in the Minch for a few weeks from the middle of April to give the fish a chance to mature.</tr>
          <ref text="400-154">td. 123</ref></li>
        <li>
          <gd>Ciamar a tha mi tomhas trèigil is siorap? Chosg e deannan math uisge teth is siabainn, gun tighinn air – ciamar a fhuair trèigil dham fhalt? — 
            siampù, mus tàinig mi chun a’ cho-dhùnaidh
            gum feumadh gu robh dòigh shònraichte aig Catrìona air faighinn timcheall air an duilgheadas seo.</gd>
          <tr>How do I measure out treacle and syrup? It [costs] quite a bit of hot water and soap, not to mention – how did treacle get in my hair? – shampoo,
            before I came to the conclusion that Catherine must have a special way of getting around this difficulty.</tr>
          <ref text="331">td. 70</ref></li>
      </ulx>
    </li>
    <li>When the stuff being quantified is already known, it is usually introduced by the partitive preposition <a href="?gd=de">de</a>
      <en>of</en> governing a specified (ie. ‘definite’) noun eg. <ul>
        <li>Dh’òl Raonaid <m>deannan <u>den fhìon</u></m>. <en>Rachel drank a little of the wine.</en></li>
        <li>Cheannaich Màiri <m>deannan <u>de mo choin</u></m>. <en>Mary bought a few of my dogs.</en></li>
      </ul>
      <ulx id="deannan_de">
        <li>
          <gd>Bhiodh poca seòladair agus na badan aodaich a chaidh aige air a chruinneachadh aig gach fear an àm fàgail an
            taighe. Bha deannan math de dh’fhir a’ bhaile a’ falbh còmhla ris a’ giùlain, fear mu seach, greis dhen phoca air a ghualainn 
            fhad ’s a bhathar a’ coiseachd nan sia mìle gu Bàgh a’ Chaisteil.</gd>
          <tr>Each man would have a sailor’s bag and the bunch of clothes that he had managed to gather together when he left the house.
            Quite a few of the the men of the town were leaving together with the [bier?], one after the other, [for a while?] of the bag on his shoulder
            while walking the six miles to Castlebay.</tr>
          <ref text="28">td. 21</ref></li>
      </ulx>
    </li>
    <li>When the stuff being quantified is already known, and has just been referred to, or can be inferred, <strong>deannan</strong> can occur on its own eg. <ul>
        <li>Dh’òl Raonaid <m>deannan</m>. <en>Rachel drank a little.</en></li>
        <li>Tha <m>deannan</m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has a few.</en></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Alternatively, <strong>deannan</strong> can be followed by one of the <a href="?gd=de">de</a> prepositional pronouns eg. <ul>
        <li>Dh’òl Raonaid <m>deannan <u>dheth</u></m>. <en>Rachel drank a little of it.</en></li>
        <li>Tha <m>deannan <u>dhiubh</u></m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has a few of them.</en></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>However, there is some variation in usage to be found here. <ulx id="deannan_de_variation">
      <li>
        <gd>Bha deannan math de shaighdearan à caochladh rèiseamaidean a seo air a rathad a-null — 
          feadhainn a chuir latha no dhà no barrachd ris an fhòrladh mar a rinn sinn fhìn.</gd>
        <tr>Quite a few soldiers from different regiments were here on the road over to there – 
          those who had spent a couple of days or more on leave as we ourselves had done.</tr>
        <ref text="400-128">td. 303</ref>
      </li>
    </ulx>
  </p>
  <p>In addition, it appears that <strong>deannan</strong> is used much more frequently with plural countable nouns, especially those describing groups of people or intervals of time, than with singular mass nouns.</p>
  <hr/>
  <p>Note the idioms <strong>deannan math</strong>
    <en>a good amount</en> and <strong>deannan beag</strong>
    <en>very few/little</en>
    <ulx id="deannan_math">
      <li>
        <gd>Ciamar a tha mi tomhas trèigil is siorap? Chosg e deannan math uisge teth is siabainn, gun tighinn air – ciamar a fhuair trèigil dham fhalt? — siampù, mus tàinig mi chun a’ cho-dhùnaidh
          gum feumadh gu robh dòigh shònraichte aig Catrìona air faighinn timcheall air an duilgheadas seo.</gd>
        <tr>How do I measure out treacle and syrup? It [costs] quite a bit of hot water and soap, not to mention – how did treacle get in my hair? – shampoo,
          before I came to the conclusion that Catherine must have a special way of getting around this difficulty.</tr>
        <ref text="331">td. 70</ref></li>
      <li>
        <gd>Bhiodh poca seòladair agus na badan aodaich a chaidh aige air a chruinneachadh aig gach fear an àm fàgail an
          taighe. Bha deannan math de dh’fhir a’ bhaile a’ falbh còmhla ris a’ giùlain, fear mu seach, greis dhen phoca air a ghualainn fhad ’s a bhathar a’ coiseachd nan sia mìle gu Bàgh a’
          Chaisteil.</gd>
        <tr>Each man would have a sailor’s bag and the bunch of clothes that he had managed to gather together when he left the house.
          Quite a few of the the men of the town were leaving together with the [bier?], one after the other, [for a while?] of the bag on his shoulder
          while walking the six miles to Castlebay.</tr>
        <ref text="28">td. 21</ref></li>
    </ulx>
  </p>
  <p>Note also the synonymous, but less common, feminine diminutive <strong>deannag</strong>.</p>
  <hr/>
</module>
