<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../module.rnc" schematypens="https://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<module status="bronze">
    <h>verbal aspect</h>
    <p>The most common verbal aspects in Gaelic are – <ul>
            <li>perfective – <ul>
                    <li>simple – <ul>
                            <li><m>Shuidh Raonaid sìos.</m>
                                <en>Rachel sat down</en>.</li>
                            <li><m>Dh’ith mi ubhal.</m>
                                <en>I ate an apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>inchoative <ul>
                            <li><m>Thòisich Raonaid air suidhe sìos.</m>
                                <en>Rachel started to sit down.</en></li>
                            <li><m>Theann mi ri ubhal a ithe.</m>
                                <en>I started to eat an apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>cessative <ul>
                            <li><m>Sguir Raonaid a shuidhe sìos.</m>
                                <en>Rachel stopped sitting down.</en></li>
                            <li><m>Stad mi a dh’ithe an ubhail.</m>
                                <en>I stopped eating the apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </li>
            <li>imperfective – <ul>
                    <li>progressive – <ul>
                            <li><m>Tha Raonaid a’ suidhe sìos.</m>
                                <en>Rachel is [in the process of] sitting down.</en></li>
                            <li><m>Tha mi ag ithe ubhal.</m>
                                <en>I am eating an apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>habitual – <ul>
                            <li><m>Shuidheadh Raonaid sìos (gu tric).</m>
                                <en>Rachel sat down (frequently)</en>.</li>
                            <li><m>Is àbhaist dhomh ubhal a ithe (gach madainn).</m>
                                <en>I usually eat an apple (every morning).</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>retrospective (the state deriving from a past event) – <ul>
                            <li><m>Tha Raonaid na suidhe.</m>
                                <en>Rachel has/is sat down.</en></li>
                            <li><m>Tha mi air ubhal a ithe.</m>
                                <en>I have eaten an apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>prospective (the state leading up to a future event) – <ul>
                            <li><m>Tha Raonaid gu suidhe sìos.</m>
                                <en>Rachel is about to sit down.</en></li>
                            <li><m>Tha mi a’ dol a dh’ithe ubhail.</m>
                                <en>I am going to eat an apple.</en></li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <section id="perfective">
        <h>perfectives</h>
        <p>A verbal expression has perfective aspect if it presents a situation (event, activity,
            process or state) from the <emph>outside</emph>, as a single, unanalysable, bounded
            whole, perhaps preceded and followed by others. In Gaelic, as in English, perfective
            situations are typically encoded in the simple past tense – <ul>
                <li><m>Dh’fhosgail</m> mi an doras. <m>Chaidh</m> mi a-steach agus <m>shuidh</m> mi
                    sìos aig a’ bhòrd. <en>I opened the door. I went in and sat down at the
                        table.</en></li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>Simple futures and conditionals can also be used to mark perfective situations in
            ‘irrealis’ contexts (non-factuals, conditionals, hypotheticals, ...) – <ul>
                <li>Ma bhios an t-uisge ann, <m>fosglaidh</m> mi an doras agus <m>thèid</m> mi
                        a-steach.<en>If it’s raining, I’ll open the door and go in.</en></li>
                <li>Nam biodh an t-uisge ann, <m>dh’fhosglainn</m> an doras agus <m>dheighinn</m>
                    a-steach. <en>If it were raining, I would open the door and go in.</en></li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p>Note also that almost all verb forms in the simple past mark perfective situations, with
            the obvious exceptions being the past simple forms of <a href="?gd=bi"><g>bi</g></a>
                (<g>bha</g>, <g>robh</g>) and <g>is</g> (<g>bu</g>). Things are more complicated with simple
            futures and conditionals, as discussed below.</p>
        <section id="inchoative">
            <h>inchoatives</h>
            <p>A perfective verbal expression has inchoative aspect if it describes the starting
                point of a situation, usually by means of an aspectual auxiliary verb – <ul>
                    <li><m>Thòisich Iain air an doras fhosgladh.</m>
                        <en>John started to open the door.</en></li>
                    <li><m>Theann Màiri ri seinn.</m>
                        <en>Mary began to sing.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=tòisich"><g>tòisich</g></a>, <a href="?gd=teann"><g>teann</g></a>
                <en>start, begin, commence</en>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="cessative">
            <h>cessatives</h>
            <p>A perfective verbal expression has cessative aspect if it describes the ending point
                of a situation, again usually by means of an aspectual auxiliary verb or verb
                compound – <ul>
                    <li><m>Sguir Iain a dh’fhosgladh an dorais.</m>
                        <en>John stopped opening the door.</en></li>
                    <li><m>Stad Màiri a sheinn.</m>
                        <en>Mary stopped singing.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=sguir"><g>sguir</g></a>, <a href="?gd=stad"><g>stad</g></a>
                <en>stop, finish, end</en>, (thig/thoir) <a href="?gd=crìoch"><g>gu crìoch</g></a>
                <en>(come/bring) to an end</en>.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="imperfective">
        <h>imperfectives</h>
        <p>A verbal expression has imperfective aspect if it presents a situation from the
                <emph>inside</emph> – ongoing and non-bounded, without explicit start or end points.
            Imperfective situations are often presented as descriptive background to foregrounded
            perfectives.</p>
        <section id="progressive">
            <h>progressives</h>
            <p>An imperfective verbal expression has progressive aspect if it describes an event,
                activity or process as continuous or ongoing – a potentially perfective situation
                that has started but not yet ended. In Gaelic, the normal way of marking progressive
                aspect is by means of verbal compounds of the form <g>bi ag</g> + verbal noun – <ul>
                    <li>Chaidh mi a-steach. <m>Bha Iain a’ leughadh.</m>
                        <en>I went in. John was reading.</en></li>
                </ul> In this example, the activity described by the second sentence is presented as
                progressive background to the foregrounded perfective event described by the
                preceding sentence.</p>
            <p>We can also have present, future and conditional progressives – <ul>
                    <li>Dè tha thu a dèanamh? / <m>Tha mi ag ithe ubhal.</m>
                        <en>What are you doing? / I’m eating an apple.</en></li>
                    <li>Feasgar a-màireach aig seachd uairean, <m>bidh Màiri a’ coimhead air an
                            telebhisean</m>. <en>Tomorrow evening at 7, Mary will be watching
                            TV.</en></li>
                    <li>Thuirt i gum <m>biodh Seumas ag obair anns a’ ghàrradh</m> an
                        làrna-mhàireach. <en>She said that James would be working in the garden the
                            following day.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>In Gaelic, it is normal to use semantically stative verbs in the progressive, where
                English would use a simple present or past – <ul>
                    <li><m>Tha mi a’ tuigsinn nan rudan seo.</m>
                        <en>I understand these things.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=ag"><g>ag</g></a> <en>in the process of</en>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="habitual">
            <h>habituals</h>
            <p>An imperfective verbal expression has habitual aspect if it describes a
                non-continuous, but ongoing, sequence/iteration of identical situations. In Gaelic,
                the traditional way of marking habitual aspect is by using simple future tense forms
                for present (and future) habituals, and simple conditional tense for past habituals,
                often elaborated or intensified by a frequency adverbial – <ul>
                    <li><m>Sgrìobhaidh mi dàn gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>I write a poem every morning.</en></li>
                    <li>Nuair a bha mi òg, <m>sgrìobhainn dàn gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>When I was young, I wrote [would write, used to write] a poem every
                            morning.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p> Note that, unlike in English, it is not appropriate to use the simple past in Gaelic
                to describe habitual aspect – <ul>
                    <li>Nuair a bha mi òg, <bad>sgrìobh mi dàn gach madainn.</bad></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>In more modern usage, the Gaelic progressive <g>ag</g> construction is often used as
                a generic marker of (introspective – see below) imperfectivity, including habitual
                aspect – <ul>
                    <li><m>Tha mi a’ sgrìobhadh dàn [ùr] gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>I write a [new] poem every morning.</en></li>
                    <li>Nuair a bha mi òg, <m>bha mi a’ sgrìobhadh dàn [ùr] gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>When I was young, I wrote a [new] poem every morning.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>Habituals can be distinguished from strict progressives by using the future
                progressive to mark present habituals and the conditional progressive to mark past
                habituals – <ul>
                    <li><m>Bidh mi a’ sgrìobhadh dàn [ùr] gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>I write a [new] poem every morning.</en></li>
                    <li>Nuair a bha mi òg, <m>bhithinn a’ sgrìobhadh dàn [ùr] gach madainn.</m>
                        <en>When I was young, I used to/would write a [new] poem every morning.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section id="retro">
            <h>retrospectives</h>
            <p>An imperfective verbal expression has retrospective aspect if it describes a
                situation that constitutes the aftermath of a preceding situation. In Gaelic, the
                normal way of marking retrospective aspect is by means of verbal compounds of the
                form <g>bi air</g> + infinitive or <g>bi an dèidh</g> + infinitive – <ul>
                    <li>Tha Iain sgìth. <m>Tha e air litir a sgrìobhadh.</m>
                        <en>John is tired. He has written a letter.</en></li>
                    <li>Chaidh mi a-steach. <m>Bha Màiri an dèidh ithe [mar-thà].</m>
                        <en>I went in. Mary had [already] eaten.</en></li>
                </ul></p>
            <p>Retrospective progressives are also possible, implying non-completion – <ul>
                    <li>Tha Iain sgìth. <m>Tha e air a bhith a’ sgrìobhadh litir.</m>
                        <en>John is tired. He has been writing a letter.</en></li>
                    <li>Chaidh mi a-steach. <m>Bha Màiri an dèidh a bhith ag ithe.</m>
                        <en>I went in. Mary had been eating.</en></li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=air"><g>air</g></a> <en>on</en>.</p>
            <p>In addition, there are a handful of Gaelic verbs that form quasi-retrospectives of
                the form <g>bi na*</g> + verbal noun – <ul>
                    <li><m>Tha mi nam shuidhe aig a’ bhòrd.</m>
                        <en>I am sat at the table.</en></li>
                    <li>Chaidh mi a-steach. <m>Bha Màiri na dùsgadh.</m>
                        <en>I went in. Mary was awake [had woken up].</en></li>
                </ul> These retrospectives appear to have similar semantic force to expressions like
                    <g>tha mi air suidhe</g> and <g>bha i an dèidh dùsgadh</g>.</p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=an^preposition"><g>an</g></a> <en>in</en>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="prospective">
            <h>prospectives</h>
            <p>An imperfective verbal expression has prospective aspect if it describes a situation
                that constitutes the prelude to a following situation. In Gaelic, the normal way of
                marking prospective aspect is by means of verbal compounds of the form <g>bi a’ dol
                    [dh]a</g> + verbal noun or <g>bi gu(s)</g> + infinitive – <ul>
                    <li><m>Tha Iain a’ dol a sgrìobhadh litir.</m>
                        <en>John is going to write a letter.</en></li>
                    <li>Chaidh mi a-steach. <m>Bha Màiri gu falbh.</m>
                        <en>I went in. Mary was about to leave.</en></li>
                </ul></p>
            <p>cf. <a href="?gd=gu-prospective"><g>gu</g></a>, <a href="?gd=impis"><g>an
                    impis</g></a>, <!--<a href="?gd=beul"><g>air bheul</g></a>,--> <a href="?gd=lunn"
                        ><g>air lunn</g></a>, <a href="?gd=tuar"><g>air thuar</g></a>
                <en>(seem to) be about to</en>. </p>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!--
    <module id="lex">
        <h lang="en">lexical aspect</h>
        <h lang="gd">...</h>
        <p lang="en">telic verbs – <ul>
                <li>intransitive – <a href="?gd=bàs">bàsaich</a>
                    <en>die</en>, <a href="?gd=caidil">caidil</a>
                    <en>fall asleep</en>, <a href="?gd=dùisg">dùisg</a>
                    <en>wake up</en>, <a href="?gd=caochail">caochail</a>
                    <en>change, die</en>, <a href="?gd=falbh">falbh</a>
                    <en>leave, depart</en>, <a href="?gd=nochd">nochd</a>
                    <en>appear, come into view/sight</en></li>
                <li>transitive – <a href="?gd=caill">caill</a>
                    <en>lose, miss</en>, <a href="?gd=fàg">fàg</a>
                    <en>leave, abandon</en>, <a href="?gd=lorg">lorg</a>
                    <en>find</en></li>
            </ul>
        </p>
        <p lang="gd">...</p>
        <p lang="en">atelic verbs – <a href="?gd=bruidhinn">bruidhinn</a>
            <en>speak, talk</en>, <a href="?gd=smaoinich">smaoinich</a>
            <en>think, reflect, believe</en>, <a href="?gd=strì">strì</a>
            <en>struggle, battle</en></p>
        <p lang="gd">...</p>
    </module>
-->
</module>
