<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../../module.rnc" schematypens="https://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<module status="bronze" id="top">
  <h lang="en">grunnan</h>
  <h lang="gd">grunnan</h>
  <p lang="en"><b>grunnan</b>
    <en>small number/group</en> is a masculine diminutive <a href="?xx=nouns/generic_quantity_nouns"
      >generic quantity noun</a>, derived from <a href="?gd=grunn">grunn</a>
    <en>number, group</en>. Dictionaries list the genitive singular <b>grunnain</b> and the plural
      <b>grunnanan</b>.</p>
  <p lang="gd">...</p>
  <p lang="en">In terms of the stuff being quantified, <b>grunnan</b> generally works like other
    generic quantity nouns, apart from the fact that it can only be followed by a plural count noun
    – <ul>
      <li>When the stuff being quantified is new information, it is usually expressed as a noun
        modifier/specifier of <b>grunnan</b> eg. <ul>
          <li>Tha <m>grunnan <u>chon</u></m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has quite a few dogs.</en></li>
        </ul>
        <ul id="grunnan_specifier">
          <li>
            <gd/>
            <tr/>
            <ref text="198">td. 54</ref>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>When the stuff being quantified is already known, it is usually introduced by the
        partitive preposition <a href="?gd=de">de</a>
        <en>of</en> governing a specified (ie. ‘definite’) noun eg. <ul>
          <li>Cheannaich Màiri <m>grunnan <u>de mo choin</u></m>. <en>Mary bought quite a few of my
              dogs.</en></li>
        </ul>
        <xl id="grunnan_de">
          <li>
            <gd>Bha <m>grunnan de ar luchd-leughaidh</m> an dùil, nuair a nochd an àireamh mu dheireadh de
              Ghairm, gu robh sin a’ strì ri buidheann shònraichte, no duine sònraichte, a chur do
              ’n Phàrlamaid, agus bha wèireichean an telefon gu math teth, uair no dhà, an déidh
              dhuinn tighinn o ’n chlò. Thog iad ceàrr sinn. [...]</gd>
            <tr>Some of our readers were expecting [?], when the last issue of Gairm appeared, that
              that was striving for a particular group [party?], or a particular person, to send to
              the Parliament, and the telephone wires were pretty hot, for an hour or two [once or
              twice?], after we came from the printers. They misunderstood us. [...]</tr>
            <ref text="600-49">td. 9, ‘Air An Spiris’</ref></li>
        </xl>
      </li>
      <li>When the stuff being quantified is already known, and has just been referred to, or can be
        inferred, <b>grunnan</b> can occur on its own eg. <ul>
          <li>Tha <m>grunnan</m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has quite a few.</en></li>
        </ul>
        <ul id="grunnan">
          <li>
            <gd/>
            <tr/>
            <ref text="2">td. 55</ref>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Alternatively, <b>grunnan</b> can be followed by one of the <a href="?gd=de">de</a>
        prepositional pronouns eg. <ul>
          <li>Tha <m>grunnan <u>dhiubh</u></m> aig Màiri. <en>Mary has quite a few of
            them.</en></li>
        </ul>
        <ul id="grunnan_de_pron">
          <li>
            <gd/>
            <tr/>
            <ref text="">td.</ref>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p lang="gd">...</p>
  <p lang="en">However, there is some variation in usage to be found here. <xl
      id="grunnan_de_variation">
      <li>
        <gd>Bha <m>grunnan de ar luchd-leughaidh</m> an dùil, nuair a nochd an àireamh mu dheireadh
          de Ghairm, gu robh sin a’ strì ri buidheann shònraichte, no duine sònraichte, a chur do ’n
          Phàrlamaid, agus bha wèireichean an telefon gu math teth, uair no dhà, an déidh dhuinn
          tighinn o ’n chlò. Thog iad ceàrr sinn.</gd>
        <tr><u>Some of our readers</u> were expecting [?], when the last issue of Gairm appeared,
          that that was striving for a particular group [party?], or a particular person, to send to
          the Parliament, and the telephone wires were pretty hot, for an hour or two [once or
          twice?], after we came from the printers. They misunderstood us.</tr>
        <ref text="400-49">td. 9, ‘Air an Spiris’</ref>
      </li>
    </xl>
  </p>
  <p lang="gd"/>
</module>
